Doctor Who (1963) S03x02 Mission to the Unknown
《神秘博士》第三季第二故事 未知领域的任务
此集故事为第三季第四故事The Daleks' Master Plan的前传
【翻译】巴蛮子sz
【时间轴】巴蛮子sz
【校对】巴蛮子sz
基于 opentitles.org 英文字幕翻译
时间轴基于动画修复版对齐
I... I remember now. I must...
我...我想起来了．我必须...
I must kill...
我必须杀...
...I must kill...
...我必须杀...
I must kill.
我必须杀
Why you ever wanted to land on a planet like this in the first place, I'll never know.
为什么你一开始就想降落在这样一个星球上, 我永远不知道
This is getting on my nerves.
我觉得有点紧张了
I hate to think what kind of an animal makes a noise like that.
我有点不敢去想，什么样的动物会发出那样的声音？
Yeah, they're getting closer.
是啊, 他们越来越近了
Yes, all the more reason to stop talking and get on with the job.
是, 我们更应该少说话, 赶紧把活儿干完
Just you listen to me, Cory.
你听我说, Cory
I know my orders were to let you have full reign
我知道我得到的命令是完全听你的
and you've certainly taken advantage of that.
而且你也很好地利用了这条命令
But as Captain of this expedition, my first responsibility is to get this ship off the ground.
但作为这个探险队的队长, 我的第一责任是让这艘飞船重新飞起来
So just... cut the chat.
那就．．别闲聊了
Some other time, hmm?
换个时间吧, 怎样？
Bring that wrench.
把那个扳手拿来
How's it going?
进展如何？
Ah, it's slow.
啊, 很慢
Flare-back melted the retaining bolts
回火溶掉了固定螺栓
it's just solid lumps of Tarnium.
都是结实的塔金属板啊
Ah, got some of it free.
啊，卸下来一些(fixme)
I want to have a look round.
我必须四周巡查一下
Listen, if we don't shoot off soon
嘿, 如果我们还不赶紧起飞
we won't make it to the rendezvous with the freighter, you know?
我们就来不及跟货船汇合了, 你知道的吧？
If we're not in the pick-up orbit, they won't wait.
如果我们那时没赶到接头的轨道, 他们不会等我们的
You'll make it, Lowery. Here you are.
我们会赶上的, Lowery．给你
I'm doing the best I can.
我尽量吧
I didn't want to touch down on this lousy planet in the first place, remember?
我一开始就不想碰这个恶心的星球的, 记得吧？
Let's not start that again.
咱们别再说这个了
Just get on with the job would you?
赶紧把活儿干完行吗？
Where the devil's Garvey?
见鬼, Garvey 又去哪儿了？
He should be back by now.
他这会儿应该在后面
No idea. Pass that screwdriver, will you?
不知道．把螺丝刀给我, 好吗？
Kill! Kill!
杀！杀！
Ahh. Managed to get some of it free.
啊，终于拆下来了(fixme)
Look at it - useless!
你看 - 这不能用了！
Get me a spare, will you?
给我一个备用的, 行吗？
No, in the ship.
没有, 在飞船里呢
Ah, it's no good, Cory.
啊, 这可不妙, Cory
You needn't bother with a spare.
你不用去找备用件了
I'm just not gonna be able to fix it.
我就没法修好它
Jeff! Jeff!
You've killed him. You've killed Jeff!
你杀死了他！ 你杀死了他！
It was him or you.
刚才他没死你就死了
You didn't give him a chance.
你都没给他留一个机会
You shot him down like an animal.
就像杀死一个动物一样开枪了
You just shot him down!
你枪杀了他！
A Varga thorn.
一根 Varga 尖刺
Wha? V... Varga?
什么？V... Varga？
Careful! Don't prick yourself with it...
小心！ 别扎到你自己．．．
or you'll end up the way Garvey is.
要不然你就变得跟 Garvey 一样了
I'd have to kill you.
我就不得不杀死你？
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
Let's get back into the ship.
我们回到飞船里说吧
What about his personal effects for his family?
他留给家人的个人物品呢？
All right. But hurry up.
没事, 快来吧
I didn't intend to tell you anything
我本来不打算告诉你任何情况的
but since we're stuck on this planet and Garvey is dead
但现在我们被困在这个星球上, Garvey 又死了
there are some facts that you're entitled to know.
有些情况你有权知道了
Yeah - Jeff Garvey's dead.
知道 - Jeff Garvey 他死了
I mean, we flew together for the last ten years
我是说, 过去十年我们都一起飞
and now he's dead, and you killed him.
现在他死了, 是你杀死了他
You'd better explain that fact and make it good.
你最好解释一下, 最好有个不错的理由
Sit down and take a look at this.
坐下, 看看这个
Huh! I might have known
哈！ 我早该知道的
"Space Security Service - Licensed to kill".
太空安全服务队 - 杀人执照
That's right.
对
Well count me out.
别把我算在内(fixme)
This other document gives me the authority to enlist the aid of any persons
这还有一份文件, 授权我可以征用任何人
civil or military. You were just enlisted.
不管是平民还是军队．现在你被征用了
From now on, Lowery, you can take your orders from me.
从现在开始, Lowery, 你得听命于我了
Yeah, all right, all right.
行, 好吧, 好吧
But I don't fully understand
但我还是没完全搞懂
better fill in a few details.
最好给我灌输点细节
All right.
行
I suppose you've heard of the Daleks?
我猜你听说过 Daleks 吧？
The Daleks invaded Earth a thousand years ago.
Daleks 在一千多年前入侵过地球
That's right.
对
Well, they haven't been active in our galaxy for some time now
而且, 他们有好一段没在我们这个星系活动了
but that doesn't mean they've exactly been sitting around.
但这并不意味着他们就在干坐着
In the last five hundred years
在过去的500年里面
they've gained control of over seventy planets in Ninth Galactic System
他们已经夺取了九大星系里面的70多个星球的控制权
and forty more in the Constellation of Miros.
还有 Miros 星座的40多个
Don't see why that should concern us.
看不出这跟我们有什么关系
I mean, they're both millions of light years away from our galaxy.
我是说, 这都离我们星系有几百万光年呢
Mmm... that's what we all thought.
唔．．．我们以前也这么想
But about a week ago, we had a report from the captain of a space freighter.
但是一周以前，我们接到一艘太空货船船长的报告
His navigator spotted a... a space ship of a type never before used in our system.
他的导航员看到了一艘太空船，那种类型从来没有在我们星系里出现过
He saw it only for a second but he gave us a good description.
他只看到了一两秒，但足够他给出了清楚的描述了
So?
怎么说？
What he described... was a Dalek spaceship.
他说描述的...是一艘Dalek太空船
Freighter XM2, freighter XM2
货船 XM2, 货船 XM2
come in please, come in please!
收到请回话, 收到请回话！
Can you make it work?
你能搞定它吗？
It's got to work!
必须搞定！
It may have been damaged in the crash.
可能在坠落的时候受损了
We must keep on trying!
我们还得再试试
Have you tested the link pulses?
你有没有测试过链路脉冲？
I know what I'm doing.
我知道我在干什么
All right, all right, so the link pulses work.
好吧, 好吧, 这么说链接脉冲没有问题
There could be something else wrong with it.
可能是别的什么地方坏了
What about the Vergometer?
伟尔热计情况怎样？
Have you tested that?
你测试过吗？
Without that you'd never break through the atmosphere.
没有这东西你别想冲出大气层
How can I possibly test that?
我怎么能够测出来呢？
We've just got to take our chance that it hasn't been damaged.
我们只能赌一把, 赌它还没有损坏了
Freighter XM2.
货船 XM2
Freighter XM2, come in please!
货船 XM2, 收到请回话！
Come in please!
请回话！
It's useless.
没用
Are you sure we can't repair this ship?
你确定我们修不好这艘船了吗？
Oh, not a chance.
哦, 一点机会也没有
So you think that the Daleks have established some sort of a base here, is that it?
这么说你觉得这些 Daleks 在这里建立了基地什么的, 是吧？
It could be. This is the most hostile planet in the universe.
有可能．这是宇宙中最有敌意的星球
People from other civilisations avoid it.
其它文明世界的人都绕开它走
I suddenly had a hunch...
我突然有种感觉．．．
that this might make an ideal place for any secret preparations that the Daleks wanted to make.
这可能是个理想的场所, 那些 Daleks 在这里秘密地准备着些什么
That's why we brought this ship down here.
这就是为什么我们把飞船降落在这里
Did you tell anybody else about this hunch of yours?
你跟别人说过你的这个想法吗？
No one - not even your commander.
谁也没有 - 即使是你的指挥官
Huh!
嘘
I just asked for a couple of men and a small rocket.
我只是申请了几个人, 还有一艘小火箭
I didn't even tell him what for.
我甚至都没有告诉他目的是什么
Then why are you telling me?
那你为什么又告诉我？
Because of this
因为这个
a thorn from a Varga plant.
来自一种名叫 Varga 的植物上的尖刺
A thing... part animal, part vegetable, looks like a cactus.
这种东西．．．半是动物, 半是植物, 看起来有点像仙人掌
The poison attacks the brain.
它的毒性直攻大脑
Rational thought is replaced by an overwhelming desire to kill.
理性思考会消失, 取而代之的是不可抑制的杀戮欲望
Eventually the poison seeps through the system
最终这种毒会渗透出来
and the victim is gradually transformed...
然后受害者就会完全变成．．．
into a Varga.
一个 Varga
Well, what's that gotta do with the Daleks?
那这跟 Daleks 又有什么关系？
The only place in the universe where Vargas grow naturally is
这个宇宙中, Varga 唯一能自然生长的地方
on the Daleks' own planet
就是 Daleks 自己的星球
Skaro.
Skaro 星球
If the Vargas are here, the Daleks are too.
如果 Varga 在这里, 那么 Daleks 也在
I will receive your reports.
我将接收你们的报告
First - space monitor control.
首先：太空监控中心
Space monitor control.
太空监控中心报告
The emissaries from the seven planets will arrive as arranged.
来自七大星球的密使已经如约抵达了
Then the conference will begin at first sun.
那么天一亮会议就开始
Security report?
安全报告？
Security control.
安全中心报告
Position of alien space craft located.
外星飞船的位置已经确定
Our patrol will reach it shortly.
我们的巡逻队将很快到达那里
The ship and its occupants must be totally destroyed.
那艘飞船和上面的乘客将会被完全消灭掉
Destroyed! Destroyed!
消灭掉！消灭掉！
It will be done.
会完成的．
Is anything out there?
外面有什么？
Vargas - they're closing in.
都是 Varga, 他们在逼近
Do you mean to say they can move?
你是说他们可以移动？
Very slowly - look.
很慢, 你看
They use their roots to drag themselves along.
它们用它们的根来拖动前行
How long are you gonna be with this... this rescue beacon?
你搞定这个东西还需要多久．．．这个求救信号？
Well this is the recording part.
这是录制部分
Let's hope it wasn't damaged in the crash.
期望它没在坠落中毁坏
We'll soon find out. Can you fix this capsule up?
很快我们就能知道．你能修好上面的舱体部分吗？
Well that's easy enough
这个很简单
but this is the recording mechanism for the message.
但这是录制消息的部分
If we sent the rocket into space without this
如果我们送入太空的火箭上缺少这个
not only would we not be rescued
不仅我们不会得救
but if you put it up early
但如果你把它挂得太早(fixme)
no one would even know we were here.
没有人会知道我们在这里
Hurry up and attach it then.
快点, 把它接上去
All right, all right!
好吧, 好吧
I'm as keen to get out of here as you are.
我跟你一样, 想快点离开这里
Give me those pliers will you?
把那钳子给我好吗？
Nearly finished.
快完成了
Good.
很好
I don't know how long we've got.
我不知道我们还有多少时间
Now the Daleks must know we're here.
现在 Daleks 一定知道我们在这里了
They'll be coming for us soon.
他们很快就会过来
Well I still think you're jumping to conclusions, you know.
我还是觉得你的推断有点跳跃
I mean, just 'cos these...
我是说, 因为这些．．．
what are they...
不管它们叫什么吧．．．
Varga things grow here
这些 Varga 长在这里
it's no proof that the Daleks are here too.
没有证据表明 Daleks 也在这里
Take my word for it, they're here all right.
相信我的话吧, 他们就在这里, 行不？
Yes, but couldn't these Varga things grow here naturally?
但这些 Varga 就不可能是在这里自然生长出来的？
I mean... it's possible, isn't it?
我是说．．．这是有可能的, 对吧？
No, they were developed in Dalek laboratories.
不, 它们是在 Dalek 的实验室里培养出来的
They grow them to give themselves protection.
他们培养它的时候给了它自我保护能力
Well if they're synthetic, that means they...
如果它们是后天造出来的, 那就意味着它们．．．
Look, stop asking questions and get on with the work!
听着, 别再这么多问题, 赶紧把活干完！
All right...
好吧．．．
Preceptor readings indicated alien space craft.
探测器数据显示出这是外星飞船
We will close on it from two directions.
我们将从两个方向逼近它
We obey.
遵命
Those things are getting too close for comfort.
这些东西靠得太近了, 不太安全
I'll fix 'em.
我就要修好了
It's no good, Lowery.
这不太妙, Lowery
They'll only grow again as fast as you can shoot them.
你打死它们, 它们又很快会长出来
At least I'll have had a try at 'em.
但至少我得试一试
Get back to the beacon.
回去搞定 beacon 吧
You sure it'll work?
你确定它能工作吗？
Well it should work
应该能
it's standard safety equipment on all rocket ships.
这是所有火箭飞船上面的标准安全设备
What does it do exactly?
它具体能干什么？
Well, you record the message, SOS
哦, 你录下口信, SOS 求救信号
on this, just like an ordinary tape recorder.
录入这里, 就像普通的录音带一样
The rocket launcher shoots it high into orbit
火箭发射器就把它送到轨道上
once it's in orbit it transmits the message
一旦它进入轨道, 它就能传送录下的口信
simple.
很简单
From what we know about the Daleks, we've got to be picked up.
以我们现在对 Daleks 的了解, 他们得赶紧把我们救走
Well it's tuned into a special frequency
．．．它就会编码到一个特殊的频率
and there are listening posts all over the galaxy.
在整个星系都遍布着接收站
Our people should get the message.
我们的人应该能收到信息
And all we have to do...
我们必须要做的．．．
is to stay alive until they get here.
就是坚持活到他们到达这里
That's the biggest rocket ship I've ever seen.
那是我见过的最大的飞船
It's like nothing we've got.
跟我们的一点也不像
It's from an outer galaxy.
它是从我们星系来的
Yeah, but what's it doing in a God-forsaken planet like this?
是, 但它到这样一个鬼星球来做什么？
I don't know.
我不知道
But I'll tell you this
但我跟你说
there's something very big going on here,
这里一定有什么大事
and if the Daleks are involved,
而且如果有 Daleks 参与的话
you can bet your life our whole galaxy is in danger!
可以打赌说我们整个星系都有危险！
The ship from the planet Gearon...
这艘飞船来自 Gearon 星．．．
...and the beginning of the Great Alliance.
．．．从而开启了大联盟时代
That should just about do it.
fixme
Give me the capsule will you.
把那个火箭给我好吗
I'll record the message.
我来录口讯
What is it?
什么东西？
There's something out there moving.
外面有什么东西在移动
Vargas?
是 Varga?
No. Moving too quickly.
不, 移动得很快
Come on, we've gotta... gotta get away.
快来, 我们得．．．得躲开
What about the distress signal?
求救信号怎么版？
Take it with us, launch it as soon as we get a chance.
带上它, 一有机会就发射
All right. Which way?
好吧, 走哪边？
Over here.
这边
They won't be the only ones, so watch out.
他们肯定不只一个, 所以小心点
Cory!
Get down and don't make a sound!
蹲下, 别出声！
The ship is empty. The crew has gone.
飞船是空的, 船员已经跑了
We will search for them.
我们要寻找他们
Destroy the ship. Fire!
摧毁这艘飞船． 开火！
It's just falling apart!
它垮掉了！
Come on!
快来！
Come on man! Come on!
快来啊, 快！
They'll be looking for us now!
他们现在在找我们
Report destruction of alien ship to control.
向控制中心报告外星飞船已被摧毁
I obey.
遵命
Advise that we will now seek out the crew.
建议我们现在开始寻找它的船员
Alert all patrols.
通知所有巡逻队员
We obey.
我们遵命
With the arrival of our ally Malpha
随着我们盟友 Malpha 的到来
we are enough.
我们都到齐了
The meeting can now begin.
会议现在开始
No it can't.
不, 还不能
What is wrong?
什么情况？
There is a hostile presence among us.
我们中间有一个坏人
What do you mean?
你什么意思？
On arrival here
我一到达这里
I am told that there are hostile influences
就被告知这里有敌对势力
from the solar system among us.
来自我们的太阳系
Not among us.
不在我们中间
Then here - on the planet Kembel.
那就是这里 - Kembel 星上
Some beings have landed from the planet Earth
有些从地球来的生物降落到这里了
hostile beings from the centre of the solar system.
来自太阳系中心的敌对生物
But do not worry, their spaceship has been destroyed.
不过不用担心, 他们的飞船已经被摧毁了
What about the beings?
那些人呢？
They cannot escape.
他们跑不了
At this moment they are being hunted down.
现在我们正在追捕他们
They will be destroyed.
他们会被摧毁
Are you sure?
你确定吗？
They cannot get away.
他们不可能逃脱
Suppose they send a message through this universe?
假如他们已经往宇宙发了信息呢？
They will not have time.
他们没有足够时间
If they do not die by our Varga plants
即使他们没死在我们的 Varga 植物上
my patrols will kill them!
我的巡逻队也会杀了他们
They will be exterminated! Exterminated!
他们会被摧毁！摧毁！
This way.
这边请
Agreed.
同意
All are agreed. It is done.
所有都同意．完成了
The seven great powers of the outer galaxies are one.
外星系七大势力已经合一
Our galactic domination... We are the mightiest in the universe!
我们的星际统治．．．我们是全宇宙最强大的！
This is indeed an historic moment in the history of the universe!
这真是宇宙历史中最具历史性的一刻
We six from the outer galaxies
我们来自外星系的六大成员
joining with the power from the solar system
与太阳系的力量合在一起
The Daleks!
The seven of us represent the greatest war force ever assembled!
我们七方代表着从未有过的强大战斗力！
Conquest is assured!
征服在即！
Mars!
火星！
Venus!
金星！
Jupiter!
木星！
The moon colonies!
月球殖民地！
They will all fall before our might.
他们都将在我们的力量前陨落
But the first of them will be...
但他们当中的第一个将是．．．
Earth!
地球！
We've got to get this capsule off and fast.
我们得把这个发射出去, 赶紧
There's a city down there - a Dalek city.
下面有一个城市 - 一座 Dalek 城市
I got quite close.
我离它很近
Close enough to hear an announcement through the loudspeaker system.
近到都可以听到他们从喇叭里面播出来的宣告
And what did they...?
他们到底在．．．
Our whole galaxy is to be invaded and destroyed!
我们整个星系要被入侵了, 恐怕不保
Kill...
杀．．．
What?
什么
You must kill...
你必须杀．．．
The Varga!
That's right.
对了
I'll soon...
我很快．．．
soon I shall be one of them...
很快我就将是它们的一员．．．
Kill... Kill!
杀．．．杀！
This is Marc Cory
我是 Marc Cory
Special Security Service
隶属特别安全队
reporting from the planet Kembel.
正在从 Kembel 星球报告情况
The Daleks are planning the complete destruction of our galaxy.
Daleks 正在计划对我们星系的全面毁灭行动
Together with the powers of the outer galaxies
参与者还有外星系的力量
a war force is being assembled...
一股武装力量已经集结起来．．．
Seismic detector is registering.
震动探测器发现情况
The crew from the rocket ship must be in this direction.
那首火箭飞船的船员一定在这个方向
Are they to be taken for questioning?
需要把他们带回去问话吗？
No.
不
They are to be exterminated.
他们将被消灭！
Destroy them on sight.
一发现就消灭他们
Destroy and exterminate!
摧毁！消灭！
We obey.
遵命
If our galaxy is to be saved
如果我们的星系有救的话．．．
whoever receives this message must relay this information to Earth immediately.
谁收到这个消息必须立刻将其转发给地球
It... it is vital that...
这．．．这非常重要．．．
defence mechanisms are put into operation at once!
防御机制必须马上开动起来！
Message ends
消息结束．
Fire.
开火
He is dead.
他死了
Our plans for the galactic conquest are safe.
我们的星际征服计划安全了
Whatever information he discovered has died with him.
他说发现的情报已经跟随他一起死了
Return to the city.
回到城市
We obey.
我们遵命
Now all is ready.
现在万事具备了
We at this table pledge our allegiance to the Dalek cause.
我们在这个桌子上宣誓效忠 Dalek 事业
Our armies will reduce the galaxies to ashes
我们的军队会把这些星系变成灰烬
their people to dust
把他们的人民变成黄土
and Earth we will conquer first.
而地球将会最先被征服
Victory!
胜利！
...Victory!
．．．胜利！
Victory! Victory! Victory!
胜利！胜利！胜利！